{"tossups": [{"question": "The Battle of Ocho Rios ended Spanish attempts to reconquer this island after Sir William Penn captured it in 1655. Samuel Sharpe led an uprising known as the Baptist\u2019s War on this island. One group of Maroons on this island resisted multiple British attacks on their settlement founded by Queen Nanny, Nannytown. This island\u2019s largest port city served as a base for privateer Henry Morgan and other pirates. For the point, name this Caribbean island, a former English colony with colonial capitals at Spanish Town, Port Royal, and Kingston.", "answer": "Colony of<b> Jamaica</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In response to this event, Detroit Major Hazen Pingree planted potato patches for the community. This event was preceded by the Philadelphia and Reading Railroad going into receivership. A drop in the gold standard after the Sherman Silver Purchase Act contributed to the onset of this event. Loans from J.P. Morgan and the Rothschild family helped alleviate, for the point, what major economic panic that dominated much of Grover Cleveland\u2019s second presidential term?", "answer": "<b> Panic of 1893</b> (accept just<b> 1893</b> after \u201cpanic\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Jim Fitzpatrick hand-painted the yellow star on one depiction of this person. Italian publisher Giacomo Feltrinelli mass-produced posters of this man after trying to negotiate the release of his acquaintance, French socialist Regis Debray. This figure was photographed at a memorial service for the victims of the <em>La Coubre</em> explosion by a man working for the newspaper<em> Revolucion</em> in 1960. For the point, name this subject of Alberto Korda\u2019s photograph<em> Guerrillero Heroicio</em>, an Argentine Marxist and participant in the Cuban Revolution.", "answer": "<b> Che</b> Guevera", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The National Revival Movement was launched in this country in an attempt to replace Cyrillic as the national alphabet. This country was the site of a rotating golden statue that always faced the sun, the neutrality monument. This country launched a copy of its national epic into space and forced schools to teach from the Ruhnama, an autobiography of its first president. Krasnovodsk was renamed in the honor of this country\u2019s most famous ruler. For the point, identify this country that was once led by Saparmurat Niyazov and has its capital at Ashgabat.", "answer": "<b> Turkmenistan</b> Page 1", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In the Season Two episode of<em> Supernatural</em> \u201cNo Exit,\u201d the ghost of this man haunts an apartment building built on the site of Moyamensing Prison, where this man was hanged in 1896 for the murder of Benjamin Pitezel. A 2003 book is split between this man\u2019s history and the history of Daniel Burnham\u2019s work on the World\u2019s Columbian Exposition. Erik Larson\u2019s<em> The Devil in the White City</em> describes this man\u2019s maze of windowless torture rooms on the top two floors of a building in Chicago. For the point, name this serial killer who built an infamous \u201cMurder Castle.\u201d", "answer": "Dr. Henry Howard \u201cH.H.\u201d<b> Holmes</b> (accept Herman Webster<b> Mudgett</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<em>Zaju</em> opera and<em> qu</em> poetry were popularized during this dynasty. The monk Drogon Phagpa created a namesake alphabet for the founder of this dynasty. That ruler of this dynasty devised a four-tier social hierarchy, which placed foreigners of the Semu caste above its Han subjects. Arab and Persian merchants led the Ispah Rebellion against this dynasty and were crushed in Quanzhou, the city where Marco Polo began his return trip to Venice after visiting this dynasty. Khanbaliq was the capital of, for the point, what Chinese dynasty ruled by Mongol emperors?", "answer": "<b> Yuan</b> dynasty [or<b> Mongol</b> dynasty before mention] Page 3", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In this battle, the 14th Brooklyn Chasseurs [shah-sirs] repeatedly charged an enemy position leading them to be labeled the \u201cred-legged devils.\u201d Despite taking Matthews Hill, the losing side in this battle was forced to retreat in what was humiliatingly dubbed \u201cThe Great Skedaddle.\u201d Witnessing the valiant defense of the Henry House in this battle, Barnard Bee exclaimed \u201cThere is Jackson, standing like a stone wall.\u201d For the point, name this battle in which Union forces ran back towards Washington D.C., the first major battle of the Civil War.", "answer": "Battle of<b> First Bull Run</b> (accept Battle of<b> First Manassas</b>; prompt on Bull Run; prompt on Manassas)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Latvian folk hero La\u02c7cplesis earned his name by ripping apart the jaws of one of these animals. Ungnyeo [oong-nyuh] was one of these animals that became human and later gave birth to the legendary founder of Korea. The ainu Iyomante ritual sacrifices these animals, whose large canine teeth were highly valued in Siberian cultures. Nanook was one of these animals worshipped by the Inuit. Hera turned Callisto into one of these animals before Zeus elevated her and her son into constellations. For the point, what large carnivore is represented by Ursa Major?", "answer": "<b> bear</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Commandos from this country boarded a Norwegian freighter carrying refugees in the Tampa Affair. In 2002, over 200 detainees protested with a hunger strike and lip-sewing in this country\u2019s Woomera Immigration Detention Center. This country\u2019s \u201cPacific Solution\u201d forbids asylum seekers arriving by boat from residing in this country, instead transporting them to detention centers in Papua New Guinea and Nauru. For the point, name this country whose mandatory detention policies were carried out by governments under Kevin Rudd and Julia Gillard in Canberra.", "answer": "<b> Australia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During one event in this city, the estate of Bush Hill was seized and turned into a makeshift hospital. The 1742 \u201cBloody Election\u201d riots in this city pitted Isaac Norris II against the Proprietary Party. A week after an event in Boston, officials in this city turned away Captain Ayers and his ship, the<em> Polly</em>, resulting in a 1773 \u201cTea Party\u201d.\u201d This city was the site of a 1793 outbreak of yellow fever that was confronted by Benjamin Rush. For the point, name this city where the Second Continental Congress met in Independence Hall.", "answer": "<b> Philadelphia</b> Page 4", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was decisively defeated after ordering cavalry to charge entrenched machine guns at the Battle of Celaya. After his army fell apart at Agua Prieta, this man began to attack foreign settlements. This commander of the Division of the North briefly forced Venustiano Carranza away from the capital with the aid of Emiliano Zapata. This man was the subject of the Punitive Expedition, where John Pershing and a young George Patton attempted to capture this man. For the point, identify this Mexican revolutionary general who raided Columbus, New Mexico in 1916.", "answer": "Francisco \u201cPancho\u201d<b> Villa</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The spirit-child Azaro observes his parents in a novel set in this country that won the 1991 Booker Prize; that novel is<em> The Famished Road</em>. One author from this country led the MOSOP movement and was executed by this country\u2019s government for protesting its relationship to Royal Dutch Shell. The first African Nobel Prize in Literature was awarded to a Yoruba playwright from this country who wrote <em>The Lion and the Jewel</em>. For the point, name this home country of Ben Okri, Ken Saro-Wiwa, and Wole Soyinka, the most populous in Africa.", "answer": "<b> Nigeria</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man was defeated at the Battle of Mikatagahara during which he ordered castle gates left open and torches lit to confuse the forces of Takeda Shingen. Stiff resistance by the Sanada at Ueda Castle prevented this man\u2019s son from reinforcing him at a 1600 battle. As head of the Eastern Army, this man defeated the forces of Ishida Mitsunari at the Battle of Sekigahara. The reign of the Toyotomi was ended by, for the point, what last of Japan\u2019s three great unifiers, the founder of a namesake shogunate?", "answer": "<b> Tokugawa</b> Ieyasu Page 5", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A memorial in front of this building is composed of 96 cast iron plates with names and the dates of their unnatural deaths. Cyrillic graffiti scrawled with charcoal in this building was preserved by Norman Foster, who also added a glass dome to this building during its reconstruction. Martin van der Lubbe was found guilty of causing one event at this building, which was used to justify a namesake decree allowing the Nazis to curtail freedoms. For the point, name this building which was set on fire in 1933 and houses the German parliament.", "answer": "The<b> Reichstag</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This composer dedicated a set of concertos titled<em> La cetra to Charles VI</em>. The marriage of Philip of Hesse-Darmstadt was celebrated by this composer\u2019s opera,<em> Tito Manlio</em>. Written to celebrate the victory over the Turks at the siege of Corfu, this composer\u2019s only surviving oratorio centers on Holofernes\u2019 siege of Bethulia. This composer of<em> Judith Triumphans</em> wrote a set of 4 violin concertos each accompanied by a sonnet; those works are part of<em> The Contest Between Harmony and Invention</em>. For the point, name this composer of<em> The Four Seasons</em>.", "answer": "Antonio<b> Vivaldi</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The main structure at this site is flanked by four bronze lions and four bas reliefs, one of which depicts the Battle of Copenhagen. Located near Charing Cross in Westminster, this site features a Corinthian column topped by a sword-wielding admiral. For the point, identify this square in London that honors Horatio Nelson.", "answer": "<b> Trafalgar Square</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This empire outlawed the possession of gold nuggets and required citizens to exchange it with gold dust. This empire\u2019s laws were written in the Kouroukan Fouga after the first meeting of the Gbara. An epic poem describing this empire\u2019s founding recounts how an arrow decorated with a rooster spur was used to defeat Sumanguru at Kirina. This empire\u2019s most famous ruler devalued the worth of gold after giving lavish gifts on his hajj to Mecca. Sundiata and Mansa Musa ruled, for the point, what West African empire that was replaced by the Songhai?", "answer": "<b> Mali</b> Empire Page 6", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This party\u2019s military killed over 3,000 people in Ba Ch\u00b4uc as part of a preemptive invasion of Vietnam. This political party supported the deposed Norodom Sihanouk as part of GRUNK, but the United States\u2019reluctance to work with him led this party to assume direct power. The Tuol Seng Museum is in a high school converted by this party to the S-21 torture center. Lon Nol was overthrown by this party whose leader called himself \u201cBrother Number 1.\u201d The Killing Fields were created by, for the point, what Pol Pot-led party that ruled Cambodia?", "answer": "<b> Khmer Rouge</b> (prompt on Cambodia before mention; do not accept or prompt on Khmer)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The Christy Commission investigated forced labor in this country. John Brown Russwurm served as governor of a colony in this country settled at Cape Palmas. After Isaac Ross died, his slaves on the Mississippi Prospect Hill Plantation were taken to this country, where the Kru and Grebo lived. Contract slavery was carried in this country under the True Whig Party. Migrants to this country settled in locations such as Harper in Maryland-in-Africa. Charles Taylor brutally ruled, for the point, what African country with its capital at Monrovia?", "answer": "<b> Liberia</b> Page 8", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}